NATHALIA ANDREA PORTILLA RINCÓN

Email: na.portilla10@uniandes.edu.co Phone: +57 3176695239 LinkedIn:www.linkedin.com/in/nathaliaportilla X/Bluesky/IG:@portillanath

Github: https://github.com/portillanath

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Microbiologist and bioinformatician with experience in research and industry for more than 8 years. Skills in molecular biology, bacteriophage biology, biotechnology application, data science (R, python, java scripting), phylogenomics, pipeline and software development, viromes, transcriptomics, and metagenomics data treatment. Interested in NGS technologies.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science (Hons) Microbiology

Universidad de los Andes. Bogotá, Colombia

October 2019

Relevant courses: Phage biology, molecular vaccine design, genomics, and bioinformatics

Master's Degree in Computational Biology

August 2021-December 2024

Universidad de los Andes. Bogota, Colombia

Computational Biology and Microbial Ecology Group- Max Planck Tandem Group

WORK EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant

Departamento de Ciencias Biológicas- Universidad de los Andes

June 2022-Current

- Viral taxonomy genomic distance profiler software development
- Metagenomics and transcriptomics workflows, microbiome applications.

Teaching Assistant-Advanced Bioinformatics Workshop for the GPS and JUNO project

Wellcome Sanger Institute March 2023 (13-24)

 Teaching material preparation, scripting on bash and docker containers pipeline for whole genome sequencing bioinformatic serotyping, variant calling, and phylogenetics. Research project formulation.

Teaching Assistant-Phylogenomics

Universidad de los Andes

August 2023 - December 2023

Teaching support for the course, guidelines, and tutorial construction IQTREE, BEAST, ASTRAL, and research class project tracking

Teaching Assistant-EBI Bioinformatics Tools

Universidad de los Andes- EBI EMBL

August December 2022, 2023, 2024

Teaching support for the course, the syllabus includes EBI databases and tools, and research class project tracking

Teaching Assistance Molecular Biology-Laboratory

Departamento de Ciencias Biológicas-Universidad de los Andes

January 2022-May 2022

Teaching classes to undergrad level, design learning material, experiment set up.Student Perception: 4.7/5.0

Molecular Biology Analyst

IPS-Integral Prevention in Health

June 2021-November 2021

- Molecular diagnosis of SARS-CoV2: Extraction (manual magnetic bead kit and MAELSTROM 4800), Master Mix preparation (Allplex), and RT PCR amplification (CFX96)
- Clinical sample reception and traceability
- Validation of results (ANNARLAB)

Research Assistant

Algae BioSolutions-CORE S.A.S. Bogotá, Colombia

September 2019- December 2020

- · Purification and classification of enterobacteria and microalgae from environmental samples
- · Isolation and characterization of coliphages for treatment
- Order of reagents and supplies, preparation of selective media
- Planning and standardization protocols (Protoplast and DNA extraction)
- Writing reports and manuscripts.
- Algae taxonomy, growth curves, and use of UV-Vis and multiparameter (pH/DO/EC) bioreactors

Graduated Research Fellow CALS

- Disease progression of dusty mildew in C.sativa variants
- Food and consumer safety training

Education Assistance- Molecular Biology (Laboratory/Theory) and Cell Biology (Laboratory/Theory)

Universidad de Los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia

August 2018- May 2019

• Purification and extraction of AND/RNA, chromatography, SDS PAGE, PCR, electrophoresis, fingerprinting, bioinformatics analysis, and academic coordination. Student Perception: 5.0/5.0

CIMIC Research Assistant

Universidad de los Andes

August 2015-May 2019

- Isolation and characterization of bacteriophages
- Formulation and profiling of bacteriophage cocktail (Salmofree patent)
- · Control of biofilms of associated clinical resistant strains to nosocomial diseases

AWARDS AND CONFERENCES

- * ISCB-Latin America SolBio CCBCOL Conference on Bioinformatics. Medellin, 2024. Poster
- Postraguated Scholarship "Fondo Vamos Juntos" .2024. Financial support for graduate students under 35 in science and technology from low-income communities.
- First Andean Host-Pathogen School. Universidad de los Andes. 2024. Participant
- IV Colombian Congress of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics.2022. Speaker
- Educational program coordinator and STEM design leader. STEM Without Borders- Club TEDed Colombia 2021
- Young Microbiologist Symposium 2020 (Southampton, UK, virtual)
- Latin American Green Award. Water category. Team FicoSucre 2020
- Ungraduated Research Fellow CALS Funding. Los Andes Foundation and Cornell University 2019.
- Congress grant the 23rd Evergreen International Phage Meeting 2019.
- SAGES Symposium Cornell AgriTech. 2019
- Best Ungraduated thesis. Department of Life Sciences. University of the Andes 2019-1
- Distinction Women in Science Allbiotech- Gender Commission 2019
- Bogotá Microbial meeting (BOOM) International Society of Microbial Ecology (ISME), American Society of Microbiology (ASM)
 2017-2020
- Scholarships "SER PILO PAGA" Colombian Ministry of Education-ICETEX 2014

REFERENCES

Alejandro Reyes Muñoz, Ph.D

Associate Professor – Department of Biological Sciences Universidad de los Andes.

+57 3102529931

a.reyes@uniandes.edu.co

Edna Matta Camacho, Ph.D

Associate Researcher- University of Carleton, Ottawa-Canada Founder STEM Foundation Without Borders +1 (438) 883-0221

+1 (430) 003-0221

edna.matta-camacho@canada.ca

Jaime Gutiérrez, Md & Ph.D/CEO&CSO

Biotechnology and Bioengineering CORE S.A.S +57 3135604293

iguitierrez@bybcore.com

Jorge Duitama, Ph.D

Associate Professor- Department of Engineering and Computation

ja.duitama@uniandes.edu.co

Martha J. Vives, Ph.D

Full Professor – Department of Biological Sciences Universidad de los Andes.

+57 3167622425

mvives@uniandes.edu.co

Gloria Esperanza Tarazona

SystemsManager at Previs IPS-Integral Prevention +57 3123774360

gerencia@previsips.com